{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This corset-maker outlined his deist beliefs in The Age of Reason and condemned \"the summer soldier and the sunshine patriot\" in an attempt to raise support for the soldiers at Valley Forge. This author of The Crisis wrote \"these are the times that try men's souls.\" For 10 points, name this pamphleteer of the American Revolution who wrote Common Sense.",
      "answer": "Thomas Paine"
    },
    {
      "question": "This book puts forth a three-phase \"salvation history\" of which the final phase is the Apostolic ministry. This book is attributed to the same author, an artist and physician, as the Book of Acts. This New Testament book is \"synoptic\" with Mark and Matthew. For 10 points, name this third book of the New Testament, a gospel which comes before John.",
      "answer": "Gospel/Book of Luke"
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this country's Communist Party wrote the Prison Notebooks and coined the concept of \"hegemony.\" This country was also home to the man whose On Crimes and Punishments founded the field of criminology, and the coiner of the 80-20 rule. For 10 points, name this homeland of Antonio Gramsci (GROM-shee) and Vilfredo Pareto.",
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "question": "A writer from this country denounced a war as \"a fight between two bald men over a comb\" in the poem Juan López y (wahn loh-pez ee) John Ward and described the endless \"Library of Babel.\" For 10 points, name this home country of Jorge Luis Borges (BORE-hays), who condemned its participation in the Falklands War.",
      "answer": "Argentina"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man shocked both Catholic and Protestant countries when he ordered the burning of Michael Servetus. This man, who explained his religious views in the book Institutes of the Christian Religion¸ advocated the \"TULIP\" philosophy as the civil authority in Geneva. For 10 points, name this founder of a strict, predestination-focused Protestant theology.",
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author corresponded with Colonel Thomas Wentworth Higginson during the Civil War,\nwhich was the subject of her poem \"It Feels a Shame to Be Alive.\" She described a carriage\ncontaining \"eternity\" in another poem. For 10 points, name this \"belle of Amherst\" whose poems\nsuch as \"Because I Could Not Stop for Death\" were published only after her death.",
      "answer": [
        "Emily Dickinson",
        "Dickinson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote about a plague in the year 2099 that kills everyone but Lionel Verney in The Last Man, which created the post-apocalyptic fiction genre. In another novel, this author created Robert Walton, who writes letters about the unjust execution of Justine Moritz. For 10 points, name this author who discussed a German scientist's creation of life in Frankenstein.",
      "answer": "Mary Shelley"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote the short stories “The Sing-Song of Old Man Kangaroo” and “How the Leopard got His Spots.” The title character of one of this man’s works is used as a pawn in the “Great Game” between Russia and Britain, and a poem by this man encourages a certain group of people to “send for the best ye breed”. For ten points, name this Victorian author of “The White Man’s Burden,” Kim, and Just-So Stories.",
      "answer": "Rudyard Kipling or Joseph Rudyard Kipling"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed to feel “nothing” after returning from exile following the White Revolution. In one speech, he referred to the United States as the “wounded snake” and the “Great Satan.” This leader’s objections to the novel The Satanic Verses led him to issue a fatwa against author Salman Rushdie. For ten points, name this Shia Islamic cleric who replaced Reza Pahlavi in the 1979 Iranian Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Ayatollah Khomeini",
        "Ruhollah Khomeini",
        "Imam Khomeini"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote “no more time’s dark events / charging like ceaseless clouds across the sky” in his elegy “Hush’d Be The Camps To-Day.” This man’s service as a volunteer nurse for the Union Army inspired the collection Drum-Taps, and he wrote an elegy in which “the great star early droop’d in the western sky”. For ten points, what poet eulogized Abraham Lincoln in “When Lilacs Last In The Dooryard Bloom’d” and “O Captain! My Captain!” from his collection Leaves of Grass.",
      "answer": "Walt Whitman or Walter Whitman"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man converted to his religion after listening to the preaching of Thomas Loe. This man wrote Innocency with Her Open Face, which led him to be imprisoned in the Tower of London, where he wrote No Cross, No Crown. This man signed a treaty with the Lenape tribe, granting him land for a colony governed by his Frame of Government. For ten points, name this Quaker who founded an American colony and its city of Philadelphia.",
      "answer": "William Penn"
    },
    {
      "question": "Donald McCraig authored a 2007 sequel to this novel about one of its central characters’ exile from Charleston. A confrontation on a staircase in this novel leads to its pregnant protagonist breaking her ribs. This novel ends with the protagonist optimistically stating that “tomorrow is another day”. For ten points, name this Margaret Mitchell novel set in Civil War-era Georgia, whose 1939 film adaptation starred Vivien Leigh as Scarlett O’Hara and is the inflation-adjusted most successful film in box office history.",
      "answer": "Gone with the Wind"
    },
    {
      "question": "The title character of this novel proves to a companion that he fought in World War I by producing a medal from Montenegro, shortly before he meets with Meyer Wolfsheim, who claims to have fixed the 1919 World Series. This novel’s narrator moved to Long Island in order to learn the bond trade and attends lavish parties thrown by the title character, who is hopelessly in love with Daisy Buchanan. For ten points, name this Jazz Age novel by F. Scott Fitzgerald.",
      "answer": "The Great Gatsby"
    },
    {
      "question": "An author from this country described spending seventeen months in a waiting line outside her son’s prison in her poem Requiem. Parasha dies during a flood in this country, causing the man who loved her to descend into madness in a poem named after an equestrian statue. For ten points, name this setting of “The Bronze Horseman,” the home country of poet Anna Akhmatova and the author of the verse novel Eugene Onegin, Alexander Pushkin.",
      "answer": [
        "Russia",
        "Soviet Union",
        "USSR",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "CCCP",
        "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, the book The Meritorious Price of Our Redemption was burned for heresy; its author, William Pynchon, founded this state’s town of Springfield. Edmund Andros was captured by rebels in what became this state in 1689, marking the end of the Dominion of New England. John Winthrop led a “Bay Colony” named after this state, which contains the site where the Pilgrims aboard the Mayflower established the Plymouth Colony. For ten points, name this state where colonists founded the city of Boston.",
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "The author of this poem got his start composing literature when he saw a hunter kill a male crane in front of its mate. A woman in this poem uses one of two boons given to her by a king to order the king’s son into a fourteen-year exile in a forest. A ten-headed figure in this poem abducts a woman and holds her captive on the island of Lanka. Hanuman aids the title character in rescuing his wife Sita in, for ten points, what Indian epic poem often compared to the Mahabharata?",
      "answer": "Ramayana"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these people, who authored a manual of their grammar called the Razos, was Raimon Vidal. Another of these people is the subject of Robert Browning’s poem Sordello. William IX, Duke of Aquitaine is often called the first of these people, whose primary output consisted of cansos and sirventes and who often used the Occitan language to tell stories about chivalrous themes. For ten points, name these medieval European poets who wrote songs of courtly love.",
      "answer": "troubadours"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a novel written in this language, Bartlebooth spends a decade learning how to paint before going on a trip around the world. Another novel in this language was written entirely without the use of the letter E as part of the Oulipo movement. Life: A User’s Manual and A Void were written by Georges Perec in, for ten points, what language in which The Stranger and No Exit were written by Jean-Paul Sartre and Albert Camus?",
      "answer": "French"
    },
    {
      "question": "This philosopher rejected that humans have a real notion of self in formulating his “bundle theory.” This thinker, who wrote a massively successful History of England, originated a problem sometimes called his “guillotine,” the Is-Ought problem. This author of “Of Miracles” divided statements into “relations of ideas” and “matters of fact.” A “missing shade of blue” was imagined by, for ten points, what Scottish philosopher who wrote An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding?",
      "answer": "David Hume"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one of this author’s novels, Urania Cabral lives under the Trujillo dictatorship in the Dominican Republic. This author, who fictionalized his time at a military academy in The Time of The Hero, created the character of Pedro Camacho, who works for Radio Panamericano during the 1950s. For ten points, name this winner of the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature, a Peruvian author who wrote Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter.",
      "answer": "Mario Vargas Llosa"
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem written during this period describes the sound of war vehicles as they approach the battle field; that poem is “The Song of Wagons.” Another poet during this period allegedly drowned after drunkenly trying to hug the reflection of the moon in a pond. Du Fu and Li Bai wrote during the rule of this dynasty, which faced the An Lushan Rebellion under Emperor Xuanzong. Empress Wu established the Second Zhou dynasty during, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty that existed between the Sui and Song dynasties?",
      "answer": "Tang Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events was named “Irma’s Injection” and was used to formulate the idea of wish fulfillment. According to one theorist, these events contain manifest and latent content that should be analyzed through therapy. That theorist wrote a book titled The Interpretation of these events, which examined several of these events experienced by the patients of that theorist, Sigmund Freud [FROYD]. For ten points, name these nocturnal events, examples of which include nightmares.",
      "answer": [
        "dreams",
        "equivalents, such as nightmares before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Authors like William Simms and Caroline Hentz wrote works in a genre named for their opposition to this novel. The title character of this novel was inspired by Josiah Henson, who wrote two autobiographies detailinghislifeafterhefledtoCanada.Manysouthernersrebuttedthisnovelbyclaimingitmisrepresented friendly relationships between masters and slaves. For ten points, name this 1852 novel by Harriet Beecher Stowe.",
      "answer": [
        "Uncle Tom’s Cabin,",
        "Life Among the Lowly"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Poet Christine de Pisan used this art form to show Reason, Justice, and Rectitude as crown-wearing women building a wall in The Book of the City of Women. The earliest depiction of Thomas Beckett’s murder is one of these works, which are characterized by marginalia and vibrant initials interspersed throughout the text. For ten points, name these medieval books filled with gold and silver embellishments and illustrations.",
      "answer": [
        "illuminated manuscript",
        "word forms like illumination"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem set during this war describes how “The larks, still bravely singing, fly / Scarce heard amid the guns below.” In a poem about this war, a man imagines a dying man’s “hanging face, like a devil’s sick of sin,” after describing an “ecstasy of fumbling” after the cries of “Gas! GAS!” A John McCrae poem about this war opens “In Flanders fields the poppies blow.” For ten points, name this war, the subject of Wilfred Owen’s “Dulce et Decorum Est,” which was written while in the hospital suffering from shell shock.",
      "answer": [
        "World War I",
        "the Great War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a 1958 book, this man faces a \"good son\" and \"good monk\" crisis in which he is twice born and his soul transformed. In that book, this man suffers an \"identity crisis\" in which, during a choir practice at a monastery, he shouts \"I am not!\" Following a similar work about Mahatma Gandhi, psychologist Erik Erikson wrote a psychobiography of this man, who challenged the Catholic Church at the Diet [[DEE-et]] of Worms [[VURMS]]. For ten points, name this Reformation leader who wrote the 95 Theses in Wittenberg, Germany.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "People serving England’s Richard II wrote a work of this type called The Forme of Cury [[KYEW-ry]]. A subversive work of this sort, authored by William Powell, provides instructions for making drugs and weapons. One of these guides, written in 1845 by Eliza Acton, contained the first known appearance of the word “spaghetti” in English print. Fannie Farmer wrote instructions for making aspic and popovers in, for ten points, works of what literary genre intended for homemakers and chefs?",
      "answer": [
        "Cookbook",
        "similar answers indicating books about preparing food"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man lost his son during the joint Allied offensive at the Battle of the Loos, inspiring his poem \"My Boy Jack.\" In a novel by this man, orphan Kimball O'Hara becomes an intelligence officer at the height of the “Great Game” in Central and South Asia between the British and Russian Empire. Inspired by the failed Jameson raid and subsequent outbreak of the Second Boer War, this author wrote the poem “If—” found in his collection Rewards and Fairies. For ten points, name this British author who set many of his works in British India like “The Man Who Would Be King” and The Jungle Book.",
      "answer": "Rudyard Kipling 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1838, W.W. Phelps and John Whitmer established Far West, Missouri based on this man’s design plan. This man died in 1844, when a mob stormed the Carthage, Illinois jail in which he was being held. This man claimed to have experienced a vision in 1823 in which an angel directed him to a buried book of golden plates, which he would later transcribe into his new church’s foundational book. For ten points, name this man, the founder of Mormonism and the Latter Day Saints movement.",
      "answer": "Joseph Smith 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker's mother supposedly took a pair of scissors and cut the cloth she had been weaving after his absence from school. This man used the example of a child falling down a well to explain innate goodness using the metaphor of the four beginnings. This thinker likely studied with the author of The Doctrine of the Mean, Zisi. This thinker recorded his conversations with various rulers in the last of the Four Books. For ten points, name this \"second sage\" who followed Confucius's ideologies.",
      "answer": "Mencius or Mengzi"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author was to be profiled by C.S. Forester after his career as a fighter pilot ended, but chose to begin his own writing career instead with an autobiographical article. He also wrote the memoir Going Solo, and this man’s Norwegian mother named him after the first man to reach the South Pole. For 10 points, name this author of James and the Giant Peach and Charlie and the Chocolate Factory.",
        "answer": "Roald Dahl"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dahl wrote the screenplays for You Only Live Twice and Chitty Chitty Bang Bang, film adaptations of books by what creator of James Bond?",
        "answer": "Ian Fleming"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author lived among the East End poor for six months to write The People of the Abyss, advocated for the genocide of China in \"The Unparalleled Invasion,\" and described a dystopian U.S. in The Iron Heel. For 10 points, name this American author who chronicled Yukon gold rushers in \"To Build a Fire\" and a novel about the dog Buck, The Call of the Wild.",
        "answer": "Jack London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What author extended London's The People of the Abyss by writing Down and Out in Paris and London before creating his own dystopia in which Winston Smith visits Room 101?",
        "answer": "George Orwell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This procedure occurred to the writer of Forever Amber and Laura. This process required the\nauthor of Johnny Get You Gun to adopt the alias \"Robert Rich.\" For 10 points, name this process\nwhich was performed on Ring Lardner, Jr., Dalton Trumbo, and others in the Hollywood Ten,\nwho were denied work in the film industry due to their membership in the Communist Party.",
        "answer": [
          "blacklisting",
          "blacklist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trumbo was publicly acknowledged as the writer of what 1961 slave uprising drama\nstarring Kirk Douglas, ending the blacklist?",
        "answer": "Spartacus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In ths play, Fluellen ironically notes that Alexander the Great killed his best friend Cleitus (CLEE-tuss) the Black. This play's prologue asks for a \"muse of fire,\" and the St. Crispin's Day speech from this play praises \"We happy few, we band of brothers.\" For 10 points, name this Shakespeare play which depicts the title king's victory at the Battle of Agincourt (AA-jin-core).",
        "answer": "Henry V"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In what other Shakespeare history play does the \"sun of York\" lament \"my kingdom for a horse\" while losing the Battle of Bosworth Field?",
        "answer": "Richard III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "H.L. Barnum argued that this author’s character Harvey Birch, the protagonist of The Spy, was based on the American Revolution soldier Enoch Crosby. This man’s best known work is a fictionalization of the defense of Fort William Henry during the French and Indian War and features Chingachgook as the title character. For ten points, name this author of The Leatherstocking Tales, the most famous of which was The Last of the Mohicans.",
        "answer": "James Fenimore Cooper"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author of The Literary Offenses of James Fenimore Cooper set his novel The Prince and the Pauper in 16th century England.",
        "answer": [
          "Mark Twain",
          "Samuel Langhorne Clemens"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One literary work set during this period is Primo Levi’s The Periodic Table, part of which details his time at Fossoli di Carpi. The first graphic novel to win a Pulitzer Prize is set during this event and stylizes the antagonists as cats and pigs. Art Spiegelman’s Maus and a book by Elie Wiesel partially set at Buchenwald are also set during this period. For ten points, name this event, the setting of Night, which is partially set at Auschwitz.",
        "answer": "the Holocaust"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Diary of Anne Frank is set in this city until its characters are deported to Bergen-Belsen concentration camp.",
        "answer": "Amsterdam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Max Weber pointed to double-entry bookkeeping as marking the beginning of notions of this concept, whose ratio to income was examined in a 2013 work by Thomas Piketty. That work about this concept “in the 21st century” dismisses its “human” type as a misnomer. Marx distinguished between its variable and constant forms in an uncompleted treatise he wrote about this concept. For ten points, name this economic concept that refers to the assets or wealth owned by a person, or to a good used in the production of other goods.",
        "answer": [
          "capital",
          "Capital in the 21st Century",
          "Das Kapital before mention"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Piketty is an author from this European country, where an economic school known as the Physiocrats believed that wealth was produced solely from land.",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man wrote a now-lost manuscript to Edmond Halley about “the motion of bodies in an orbit.” A constant sometimes named for this man was first measured using a torsion balance by Henry Cavendish and is written as big G. One law named for this man technically says that the derivative of momentum with respect to time is equal to the force, but is more commonly written F = ma [F equals m times a]. For ten points, name this English physicist and namesake of three laws of motion.",
        "answer": "Sir Isaac Newton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Newton described his theories of classical mechanics, including his laws of motion, in this book. Bertrand Russell and Alfred Whitehead wrote a book with this title that attempted to formally prove all of mathematics.",
        "answer": "Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One novel by this author sets scenes at a tavern named The Boot, which was used by the participants in the Gordon Riots. Another novel by this author is partially set at Satis House, inspired by a mansion of the same name in Kent, where the widow Miss Havisham lives; in that novel, a convict who is sent to Australia makes a fortune and becomes the benefactor of Pip. For ten points, name this British author of serial novels like Barnaby Rudge and Great Expectations.",
        "answer": "Charles Dickens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Dickens’s Sketches by Boz involves a visit to what notorious London prison, the birthplace of DeFoe’s Moll Flanders and temporary residence of Ben Jonson after his duel with Gabriel Spenser?",
        "answer": "Newgate Prison"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Recruitment posters for this war encouraging American soldiers to “Destroy this mad brute!” show an angry gorilla wearing a pickelhaube. During this war, which coincided with the Dada movement, John Singer Sargent painted blindfolded soldiers returning after being mustard gassed at the Battle of Ypres [eep]. The author of “Dulce et decorum est,” Wilfred Owen, died in, for ten points, what war that lasted from 1914 to 1918?",
        "answer": [
          "World War I",
          "the Great War",
          "the War to End All Wars"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another work of World War I-era literature is this novel by Erich Maria Remarque, in which Paul B¨aumer is urged to join the German army.",
        "answer": "All Quiet on the Western Front or Im Westen Nichts Neues"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a novel set in this country, Aurora de Gama falls in love with the manager at her father’s spice warehouse; that novel takes its name from the dying reaction of Boabdil and is titled The Moor’s Last Sigh. A group of telepathic youths hold a conference in this country in a novel in which Saleem Sinai was born at the exact moment of this country’s independence. For ten points, name this setting of Salman Rushdie’s novel Midnight’s Children.",
        "answer": "India"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rushdie’s Satanic Verses prompted this Supreme Leader of Iran to issue a fatwa against him in 1989.",
        "answer": "Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Clausius’inequalitywasanearlyformulationofalawconcerningthisquantity,whosepublicawareness grew through Isaac Asimov’s short story “The Last Question.” Early theories on this quantity were developed by Lazare Carnot [la-zarr car-noh], whose namesake cycle conserves this quantity. Ludwig Boltzmann’s tombstone has an equation for this quantity engraved on it. According to the second law of thermodynamics, this quantity always increases within isolated systems. For ten points, name this measure of disorder within a system.",
        "answer": "entropy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The second law of thermodynamics inspired this Czechoslovakian dissident, who wrote that “the basic law of life is to be ever more highly structured and to struggle against entropy” in an open letter to Gustav Husak in 1975. This writer became President of Czechoslovakia in 1989.",
        "answer": "V´aclav Havel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location experienced a population surge after the Battle of White Marsh. At this location, a work on “Regulations for the Order and Discipline” was translated into the “Blue Book.” One general’s inaction while at this location led to the Conway Cabal plot, which aimed to replace him with Horatio Gates. For ten points, name this location that served as Washington’s winter quarters for the Continental Army from 1777 to 1778.",
        "answer": "Valley Forge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Prussian officer wrote the aforementioned “Blue Book” and trained the American army as Washington’s inspector general.",
        "answer": [
          "Baron von Steuben",
          "Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author bolstered the reputation of Florida as a tourist destination through a book of letters titled Palmetto Leaves. This author was a close friend and travel companion of Elizabeth Campbell, the Duchess of Argyll. This author, who painted an unflattering portrait of Aaron Burr in The Minister’s Wooing, also wrote a novel in which Eva St. Clair urges those around her to convert to Christianity and Simon Legree orders one of his slaves to be beaten to death. For ten points, name this author of Uncle Tom’s Cabin.",
        "answer": "Harriet Beecher Stowe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Stowe’s novel Dred is subtitled “A Tale of” this location, where a community of escaped slaves thrived in the early 19th century. This marshy area stretches from Norfolk in Virginia south to Edenton in North Carolina.",
        "answer": "Great Dismal Swamp"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The writing of this work was prompted by Marjorie Spock’s legal actions on Long Island. Edwin Diamond, who was originally commissioned to co-write this book, scathingly critiqued its author after she was hired by the New Yorker to write an article on the same subject. This book highlighted bioaccumulation as a cause of the title, bleak condition of nature. For ten points, name this landmark 1962 environmental study that argued for the ban of DDT and other pesticides, written by Rachel Carson.",
        "answer": "Silent Spring"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This major producer of DDT lobbied heavily against Silent Spring when it was first published. This developer of nylon and Teflon merged with Dow in 2017.",
        "answer": [
          "DuPont",
          "DowDuPont"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a poem set during this war, a daughter of the nobleman Kochubei named Maria falls for the central character; that poem was inspired by a Lord Byron work about a figure in this war who served under John II Casimir. A story about the victor of this war describes a storm on the river Neva and sees Evgenii find the title statue of this war’s victor staring at him. For ten points, name this war described in poems like “The Bronze Horseman” and “Poltava,” a victory for Peter the Great.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“The Bronze Horseman” and “Poltava” are poems by this Russian poet who was exiled by Alexander I and killed in an 1837 duel.",
        "answer": "Alexander Pushkin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A policeman complained “I have just bought some new furniture” when he was suspended from his job in 1963 after the revelation that he had arrested this author years earlier. This author, who called herself a “bundle of contradictions,” addressed her work to a character she created named “Kitty.” For ten points, name this author who died in Bergen-Belsen concentration camp after writing a diary in hiding.",
        "answer": "Annelise Mary “Anne” Frank"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anne Frank’s family hid in a house on the Prinsengracht canal in a series of rooms known by this name, which was also the original title of Anne’s diary when it was first published.",
        "answer": "the Secret Annex or Het Achterhuis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Scholars recognize that this book was written as the second volume of a work, of which Luke is the first volume. In the early part of this book, the Holy Spirit descends upon the Christians in Jerusalem, who begin speaking in tongues. Later in this book, Saul changes his name to Paul after being blinded on the road to Damascus. For ten points, name this book detailing the history of the first-century Christian church, which immediately follows the Gospels in the New Testament.",
        "answer": "Acts of the Apostles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Acts, Paul is shown “unusual kindness” on this island, where he was shipwrecked on his way to Rome.",
        "answer": "Malta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who was the first to reprint a Masonic book in America, compiled thirteen virtues in his unfinished autobiography. This ambassador to France obtained the letters of Thomas Hutchinson, and drew a political cartoon of a chopped-up snake with the words “Join or Die” to support his Albany Plan. For ten points, name this Founding Father and author of Poor Richard’s Almanack, who performed a famous kite experiment in a thunderstorm.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As a teenager, Franklin wrote letters to his brother’s newspaper, the New-England Courant, under this pen name.",
        "answer": "Mrs. Silence Dogood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Giangiacomo Feltrinelli was the first to publish this author’s most famous work after it was smuggled out of its native country. The CIA declassified dozens of documents about its role in supporting that work by this author, which begins with the funeral of the title character’s mother Marya and is interspersed with scenes between the title character and Lara Antipov. This man claimed that leaving Russia would be “tantamount to death” as one of his reasons for declining the 1958 Nobel Prize in Literature. For ten points, name this Russian author of Dr. Zhivago.",
        "answer": "Boris Pasternak"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The CIA pushed for the Nobel Prize to be given to Pasternak, whose work was primarily published in Russia in this underground, illegal form that sought to avoid Soviet censorship.",
        "answer": "Samizdat"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country is the setting of the novel No One Writes to the Colonel, which depicts an unnamed soldier in the Thousand Days’ War. Riots were sparked after a disgruntled youth assassinated the liberal leader Jorge Eli´ecer Gait´an, leading to La Violencia. The 2016 Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to this country’s president, Juan Manuel Santos, for brokering a treaty that failed after a public referendum. For ten points, name this country where FARC rebels opposed the government in Bogota.",
        "answer": "Colombia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "No Ones Writes to the Colonel is a novel by this Colombian Nobel laureate who discussed the Medellin cartel in News of a Kidnapping and wrote One Hundred Years of Solitude.",
        "answer": "Gabriel Garcia Marquez"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man translated the Pastoral Care to help local bishops train priests; that work is the oldest known English book. This man, who had his life chronicled by Asser, promulgated his law code within the “Doom Book.” This man’s victories at Edington and Chippenham against Guthrum pacified the Viking threat. The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle was published during the reign of, for ten points, what “great” king from Wessex?",
        "answer": "Alfred the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pastoral Care, the oldest known book in English, is a translation of a work by this “great” pope, who sent a mission to England in 596. His reforms to church liturgy included a larger use of plainchant.",
        "answer": [
          "Gregory I",
          "Saint Gregory the Great",
          "Gregorian chant"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a lecture, this author emphasized his home country’s proverb that “ONE WORD OF TRUTH SHALL OUTWEIGH THE WHOLE WORLD.” This man delivered that lecture by letter, as he expected he would be forced into exile if he traveled to Stockholm to accept the 1970 Nobel Prize in Literature. This author’s experiences in the Main Directorate of Camps and those of hundreds of other political prisoners was published via samizdat. For ten points, name this Soviet dissident author of One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich and The Gulag Archipelago.",
        "answer": "Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Gulag Archipelago relates the history of Soviet labor camps from 1918 until this February 25, 1956 event. Journalists were not invited to this event, which lasted four hours in the middle of the night at the Kremlin.",
        "answer": [
          "Nikita Khrushchev’s Secret Speech",
          "descriptions relating to Khrushchev delivering the speech “On the Cult of Personality and its Consequences”"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a book condemning this event, a thinker stated “Kings will be tyrants by policy when subjects are rebels from principle.” Mary Wollstonecraft responded to that book condemning this event with a book defending republicanism titled A Vindication of the Rights of Men. Edmund Burke argued for gradual change in a book titled Reflections on, for ten points, what event that was triggered by the fall of the Bastille?",
        "answer": "French Revolution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two years after writing A Vindication of the Rights of Men, Wollstonecraft published A Vindication of the Rights of Woman, which attacked this French politician’s attempt to deny women public education. This foreign minister under Napoleon represented France at the Congress of Vienna.",
        "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand-P´erigord, Duke of Talleyrand"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A philosopher from this country created the Black Repartition and the \"Emancipation of Labor Group,” and authored The Development of the Monist view of History. Another author from this country, an anarchist who spent 41 years in exile in Switzerland, worked with Jean Grave on the Manifesto of the Sixteen and authored The Conquest of Bread. Georgi Plekhanov and Peter Kropotkin were philosophers from, for ten points, what country once ruled by the Tsars?",
        "answer": "Empire of Russia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Georgi Plekhanov is considered the \"father\" of this social and economic philosophy in Russia, based on the work of a German philosopher who co-wrote The Communist Manifesto with Friedrich Engels.",
        "answer": [
          "Marxism",
          "Marxist"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first person to win this award was Dorothy P. Lathrop for her work titled Animals of the Bible. Barbara Cooney won this award twice, first for Chanticleer and the Fox, and then for The Ox-Cart Man. The first novel to be given this award was Brian Selznick’s The Invention of Hugo Cabret, and the most recent winner of this award was We Are Water Protectors by Michaela Goade. This is Not My Hat, Jumanji, and Where the Wild Things Are have all received, for ten points, what award given for excellence in picture book illustration?",
        "answer": "Caldecott Medal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What book, which inspired nine statues in Boston Public Garden and was named the official children’s book of Massachusetts, was the first of Robert McCloskey’s two Caldecott winners?",
        "answer": "Make Way for Ducklings"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man explained how different groups could unite to create basic social constructs with the term “overlapping consensus.” This man wrote an essay that is subtitled \"Political not Metaphysical\" which focuses on the principles of liberty and equality. One of this man's works includes the idea of improving the position of the worst off, known as the “difference principle.” This man created a thought experiment based on the “veil of ignorance.” For ten points, name this philosopher who wrote A Theory of Justice.",
        "answer": "John Rawls"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This philosopher responded to Rawls with his libertarian work, Anarchy, State and Utopia. He created the idea of evolutionary cosmology in Invariances.",
        "answer": "Robert Nozick"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who spent five years in exile in the Netherlands, argued that \"the end of law is...to preserve and enlarge freedom.\" While serving as a secretary, this man authored the Fundamental Constitutions of Carolina. Thomas Jefferson included many of this man's ideas in the Declaration of Independence, although he edited \"property\" to \"the pursuit of happiness.\" For ten points, name this British \"Father of Liberalism\" who wrote two Treatises on Government.",
        "answer": "John Locke"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Locke determined that people are inherently rational, unlike this predecessor of his, who described life as \"solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short\" in his work Leviathan.",
        "answer": "Thomas Hobbes 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author created Sylvia Gellburg, a Jewish woman who falls victim to psychosomatic paralysis after reading an article about Kristallnacht. The outing of this writer's Communist sympathies by his former friend Elia Kazan to the House Un-American Activities Committee was parodied in his play, A View from the Bridge. Joe Keller knowingly ships defective aircraft parts during the Second World War in this author's play All My Sons. The author of The Crucible was, for ten points, which mid-20th century playwright?",
        "answer": "Arthur Miller or Arthur Asher Miller"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Miller's most famous spouse was which film icon who was known for playing comedic blondes in films like Some Like It Hot and The Seven Year Itch?",
        "answer": "Marilyn Monroe or Norma Jeane Mortenson"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Rise of Nazism",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Alcoholic beverage that names a failed “Putsch” by the Nazis.",
          "answer": [
            "Beer",
            "Beer Hall Putsch"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Book written by Adolf Hitler while in prison, outlining his ideology.",
          "answer": [
            "Mein Kampf",
            "My Struggle"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German Parliament building set on fire by a Dutch communist.",
          "answer": "Reichstag"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite Nazi unit who killed political opponents in the “Night of the Long Knives.\"",
          "answer": [
            "SS",
            "Schutzstaffel"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "World War One hero whose weak presidency allowed the Nazis to suspend civil liberties.",
          "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Semitic paper published by Julius Streicher which spread Nazi propaganda.",
          "answer": [
            "Der Sturmer",
            "The Stormer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Gay leader of the SA and member of the Nazi “Old Guard,” executed during the “Night of the Long Knives.”",
          "answer": "Ernst Röhm"
        },
        {
          "question": "1933 Act which gave Hitler the power to circumvent the president and his cabinet.",
          "answer": "Enabling Act 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote about the execution of John Brown in “The Portent,” the first poem in his unpopular collection Battle-Pieces, and described his visit to the Middle East in Clarel. He described fraudsters on the Mississippi River in The (20 pts)",
        "Confidence Man, and created the characters of Stubb, Flask, and (10 pts)",
        "Starbuck in another novel. For 10 points, name this American author of nautical tales such as “Billy-Budd” and a novel set on the Pequod, Moby- Dick."
      ],
      "answer": "Herman Melville NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A novelist from this country wrote the script for the original car-chase movie Vanishing Point and the experimental book Three Trapped Tigers. The national poet of this country wrote the (20 pts)",
        "Versos Sencillos (VAIR-sos sen-SEE-yos), which contains a version of (10 pts)",
        "\"Guantanamera\" (GWAN-tah-nah-MAY-ruh). For 10 points, name this country where Jose Martí once wrote against Spain and poets such as Reinaldo Arenas have been suppressed by the Castro regime."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Cuba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man refuted the Patriarcha of Robert Filmer in a close reading whose sequel introduced the concept of \"mixing labor\" with land to create property. This man's (20 pts)",
        "Some Thoughts Concerning Education expanded on his concept of the mind as a (10 pts)",
        "\"tabula rasa\" or \"blank state.\" He wrote slavery into the constitution of the Carolinas. For 10 points, name this author of Two Treatises on Government which advocated a positive, non-Hobbesian notion of the social contract."
      ],
      "answer": "John Locke"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work was first published in serial form in the newspaper Appeal to Reason. The cousin of the protagonist’s wife is forced into prostitution, shortly after Ona’s death in childbirth. A rousing cry of “Chicago will be ours!” distracts the protagonist of this novel at its end. (20 pts)",
        "Theodore Roosevelt privately described an “utter contempt” for this novel’s author, though he signed legislation creating the (10 pts)",
        "FDA after this novel “hit the public’s stomach”. For ten points, name this muckraking novel about Jurgis Rudkus, a Lithuanian immigrant working in the meat-packing industry, written by Upton Sinclair."
      ],
      "answer": "The Jungle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The novels No Longer Human and The Setting Sun are characteristic of the “I-novel” style developed in this country in the 1940s. The short story “Patriotism” follows the aftermath of a coup in this nation; the same author wrote a fascist play, (20 pts)",
        "My Friend Hitler, before his death in an attempted coup d’etat in 1970. The burning of the (10 pts)",
        "Golden Pavilion in this country inspired a 1956 novel narrated by Mizoguchi. The authors Osamu Dazai and Yukio Mishima are from, for ten points, what Asian country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Japan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The novel Ice Candy Man centers around this historical event, and a novel awarded the “Booker of Bookers” revolves around the consequences of this event. Freedom at Midnight is a non-fiction work that describes the (20 pts)",
        "atrocities that occurred during this historical event, and children such as Shiva “of the Knees” and Parvati-the-witch have (10 pts)",
        "special powers because they were born during this event. For ten points, name this August 15, 1947 event that was chronicled by Salman Rushdie in Midnight’s Children in which two countries were created."
      ],
      "answer": "Partition of India"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man “learned good morals” from his grandfather Verus, according to a work written while on campaign in Pannonia against the Quadi. During this man’s rule, the Antonine Plague killed his co-ruler, Lucius (20 pts)",
        "Verus. This father of Commodus wrote a 12-book work based on the ideas of a school founded by (10 pts)",
        "Zeno of Citium. For ten points, name this last of the Five Great Emperors and author of the Stoic book Meditations."
      ],
      "answer": "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The original recitation of this work supposedly caused one listener to faint upon hearing the name of her son, Marcellus, mentioned. The executors of this work were ordered to publish this work after its author’s death, regardless of his wishes, and this work’s patron was the nobleman (20 pts)",
        "Maecenas. This work’s title figure wins the hand of Lavinia after defeating Turnus, and (10 pts)",
        "Augustus championed this work because he saw himself as an incarnate of its hero, who escaped from the Trojan War. For ten points, name this epic poem by Virgil about the title Trojan prince."
      ],
      "answer": "The Aeneid"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The history and end of this policy are recounted in My Traitor’s Heart, written by the exiled Rian Malan. A person who was imprisoned because of this policy documented his (20 pts)",
        "incarceration in the book Long Walk to Freedom. The breakdown of this policy provides the backdrop of Nadine Gordimer’s novel July’s People, in which the Smales family flees from (10 pts)",
        "Johannesburg. Nelson Mandela opposed, for ten points, what discriminatory policy of South Africa?"
      ],
      "answer": "Apartheid"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote that he had once visited the “third heaven” and seen “things man is not permitted to tell.” Though he longed to travel to Bithynia, a vision inspired a visit to Macedonia instead. This man, who miraculously survived a (20 pts)",
        "snakebite in Malta following a shipwreck, approved of the martyrdom of Stephen before falling to the ground and becoming blind in a (10 pts)",
        "conversion experience on the road to Damascus. For ten points, name this early Christian apostle and author of much of the New Testament."
      ],
      "answer": "Paul or Saul of Tarsus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This civilization produced the Linen Book of Zagreb, the only surviving book made of linen, as well as the Sarcophagus of the Spouses. This civilization’s language was long considered to be an (20 pts)",
        "isolate and uses large clusters of consonants due to a stress on the initial syllable. A loss at the Battle of Veii signaled the fall of this civilization, which referred to themselves as the Rasena. (10 pts)",
        "Lars Porsena was a leader of, for ten points, what northern Italian civilization that was led by Tarquin the Proud before it was assimilated into Rome?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Etruscans",
        "Rasenna before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This novel fictionalizes John Felton as a Puritan who is deceived by his lover into murdering the Duke of Buckingham. A central plot point of this novel is the recovery of a group of diamond studs that Queen (20 pts)",
        "Anne is asked to wear to a royal party. In this novel, Milady de Winter acts as an agent of (10 pts)",
        "Cardinal Richelieu and vengefully poisons the woman who falls in love with D’Artagnan [dar-tan-yan]. For ten points, identify this Alexandre Dumas novel named after a trio of French soldiers."
      ],
      "answer": "The Three Musketeers or Les Trois Mousquetaires"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man engineered a worker’s cult around mangoes that lasted for one and a half years. This leader advised people to bang pots and pans in his (20 pts)",
        "Four Pests campaign; the resulting loss of sparrows caused a boom in the locust population. This leader baited anti-regime intellectuals with a brief period of liberalization known as the (10 pts)",
        "Hundred Flowers Campaign. Lin Biao and Zhou Enlai advised, for ten points, what the author of the Little Red Book and founder of the People’s Republic of China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) African-American soldier William Williams was one of four men killed during an attack on this fort carried out by Alexander Cochrane. This fort held an object created by Mary Pickersgill that inspired a poem later (20 pts)",
        "set to the tune “To Anacreon in Heaven;” that poem was written by a lawyer visiting (10 pts)",
        "Baltimore who observed an attack on this fort in 1814. For ten points, name this fort whose defense inspired Francis Scott Key to write the words of “The Star-Spangled Banner.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Fort McHenry"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Michelle Alexander argued that these institutions perpetuate a racial underclass in her book The New Jim Crow. Jeremy Bentham designed a type of these institutions that Foucault later discussed in a book subtitled for “The (20 pts)",
        "Birth of” them. A subject nicknamed “John Wayne” was one person whose abuses led Philip Zimbardo’s (10 pts)",
        "experiment simulating these institutions to end after only 6 days. A 1971 Stanford University experiment replicated, for ten points, what type of facility where criminals are incarcerated? ANSWER:prisons(orjails;orcorrection(s)centers/facilities;orpenitentiaries;promptondescriptive answers relating to the justice system in the first sentence) (4) This man adopted the Plan of Cuernavaca and the Seven Laws, though he dissolved Congress afterwards regardless. This man was removed from power by the Plan of Ayutla after serving (+) 11 non-consecutive terms. During the Pastry War against the French, this man was struck by a cannon at (*) Veracruz and had his amputated leg buried with full military honors. For ten points, name this Mexican general who failed to thwart the Texan Revolution, despite leading forces at the Alamo."
      ],
      "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author wrote a work in which Pope Innocent XII is asked to overturn the conviction of the count Guido Franceschini, The Ring and the Book. This author inserted the ironic phrase “God’s in his heaven, all’s right with the world,” in the (20 pts)",
        "“Pippa Passes” piece for the Bells and Pomegranates series. This author’s most famous poem is suspected to be about Alfonso Il d’Este, the Duke of Ferrera, and his murdered wife Lucrezia d’Medici, whom he describes as having a heart (10 pts)",
        "“too soon made glad.” For ten points, name this Victorian poet of My Last Duchess, the husband of the author of Sonnets from the Portuguese."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Browning"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure advises a king who goes mad and lives in the wilderness until his “hair grew like feathers” in a book that describes the rise of Darius the Mede, an otherwise unattested king who ruled before (20 pts)",
        "Cyrus the Great. As an adviser to the Babylonian king Belshazzar, this figure interprets mysterious writing that (10 pts)",
        "appears on a wall. This figure’s namesake book contains the story of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. For ten points, name this Biblical adviser of Nebuchadnezzar who miraculously survived being thrown into the lion’s den."
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Octavio Paz invited this man to a 1990 conference where he cited the example of the PRI to claim that “Mexico is the perfect dictatorship.” As a FREDEMO party candidate, this man won the first round of a 1990 presidential election but lost the run-off to a dark horse candidate from the right-wing Cambio 90 ticket, (20 pts)",
        "Alberto Fujimori. The dictatorship of Manuel Odria is the setting of Conversation in the Cathedral, a (10 pts)",
        "novel by, for ten points, what Peruvian politician and author of Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter who won the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mario Vargas Llosa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This union published the Hungarian newsletter Bérmunkás. Members of this union were charged with treason as the Sydney Twelve after the Tottenham Tragedy. \"Slim\" Evans, part of the On-To-Ottawa trek, was once a member of this group, which was housed in the Finnish (*) Labor Temple in Canada. This union made the Little Red Songbook and wrote songs like \"There'll Be Pie in the Sky.” Mother Jones and (*) Big Bill Haywood were among the founders of this group, which advocated \"one great union.\" For ten points, name this labor union of \"Wobblies.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Industrial Workers of the World",
        "IWW",
        "Wobblies before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first edition of this book contained 200 selected quotations across 23 topics, including “Correcting Mistaken Ideas,” “The Mass Line,” and “Political Work.” An endorsement in this book’s second edition was removed in 1971 after the endorser died in a (20 pts)",
        "Mongolian plane crash and was labeled a traitor. Until the later years of its author’s rule, each (10 pts)",
        "Chinese citizen was required to carry a copy of this book at all times, and it is commonly cited as one of the most published books in history. For ten points, name this book, a collection of statements by Mao Zedong."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Little Red Book",
        "Quotations from Chairman Mao Zedong or Mao Zhuxi Yulu 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A preacher with this surname criticized striking railroad workers, saying that \"the man who cannot live on bread and water is not fit to live,\" causing cries at labor rallies of “Hang (this surname).” That man with this surname raised money to buy (20 pts)",
        "rifles during the Bleeding Kansas crisis that came to be known as his namesake \"Bibles.” Abraham Lincoln said that an author with this (10 pts)",
        "maiden name, “Wrote the book that started this great war.\" For ten points, what surname was shared by preacher Henry Ward and his sister, the author of Uncle Tom's Cabin, Harriet Stowe?"
      ],
      "answer": "Beecher"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's lover is shown in the Mondragone marble statue and was celebrated by Karl Heinrich Ulrichs using the pen name \"Numa Numantius\". Pnacrates wrote a poem about this man's heroism, about which a tondo was later placed on Arch of (20 pts)",
        "Constantine. This man's lover was with him when he killed the Marousian lion and was the Bithynian Greek Antinous. This man rebuilt the Serapeum of Alexandria and the (10 pts)",
        "Pantheon. In Judaea, this man ended the Bar Kokhba revolt. For ten points, name this successor of Trajan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hadrian",
        "Caesar Traianus Hadrianus 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A man named Antipholus [[ahn-TEH-foh-lus]] and his servant Dromio, both residents of this island, travel to Ephesus [[eh-FUH-sus]] in search of their respective twins in the Shakespearean play The Comedy of Errors. Italian writer Luigi Pirandello wrote his play (*) Six Character's in Search of an Author in this island's native dialect. Johann Wolfgang von Goethe [[GUR-tuh]] wrote a travelogue about climbing Mt. (*) Etna on, for ten points, what southern Italian island?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sicily",
        "Sicilia 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A character in this novel, based on a historical warlord also known as Xuande [[SHWAHN-DEH]], throws his infant son to the ground after General Zhao Yun [[ZHOW-YUN]] risks his life to save him during the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Changban [[CHAHNG- BAHN]]. The Battle of Red Cliffs appears in this novel which relates the campaigns of Cao Cao [[KOW-KOW]] (10 pts)",
        "and Zhuge Liang [[TCHOO-guh LYAHNG]]. Luo Guanzhong [[LWOH GWAHN-ZHOHNG]] wrote, for ten points, what historical “Romance” set during a namesake period of Chinese history?"
      ],
      "answer": "Romance of the Three Kingdoms or Sānguó Yǎnyì 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
    }
  ]
}